<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discovery of malignants. By the known lawes, and will of the King, absurdly urged against the Parliament, by the people, lawyers, judges, jury, divines, and King forced from the truth by willfull errour.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81529</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871353</idno>
  <idno type="VID">123763</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942076</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E106_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212782</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871353</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871353e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81529)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 19:E106[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discovery of malignants. By the known lawes, and will of the King, absurdly urged against the Parliament, by the people, lawyers, judges, jury, divines, and King forced from the truth by willfull errour.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Thomason annotation:"June the 14. 1643".</note>
                  <note>Leaf A1 missigned B.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Great Britain. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:123763:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Discovery of</hi> MALIGNANTS.</head>
            <head type="sub">By the knowne Lawes, and will of the KING, absurdly urged against the PARLIAMENT, by the People, Lawyers, Judges, Jury, Divines, and King forced from the Truth by willfull errour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Austin</hi> defines a people by their association, and <hi>Aristotle</hi> by their Constitution, and <hi>Fortescue</hi> out of both by their intention, Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and subjection. A people (saith the Father) is <hi>a company of men associated by the consent of Law, and communion of prosit,</hi> and the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher to give them an head addes, <hi>when one is constituted of many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves, one shall be the Ruler, and the rest the ruled.</hi> By one, he meanes not a person but a power, not a <hi>King</hi> but a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for one is not <hi>unus homo,</hi> but <hi>unum Consilium,</hi> not one man, but one Senate or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dership, which is the most ancient and best approved Government both in Church and State, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.4. for it is Reason and prudence that Rules best, and both are found in the Elders of the people, which is the Reason the Almighty placeth the Councell, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. before the <hi>King, V.</hi> 14. and referres all persons to the judgement of the Elders, and leaves it no where to the King, and the Lawyer I mentioned binds the <hi>King</hi> to the Law, which he compares to the ligaments of the body, that the head may not change; and he compares the people to the heart, that live first and die last in any Kingdome, and all confesse that the safety of the people is the supreme Law. Their intention lives first, and provides the meanes to make happy the head in direction, and the hand in execution, and I conceive that to be the Reason why <hi>Barons</hi> and <hi>Bishops</hi> refusing to come to Parliament, the <hi>King</hi> with his <hi>Commons</hi> may take care of the Kingdomes safety: but without the Commons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, nothing may be done by either, for if the intention of the people live first, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish that and life ceaseth; and now to discover Malignants without the touch of any mans person, I shall by demonstration teach it in two things. First, the knowne Lawes urged by ignorance against them, that onely know them by the confession of all. Secondly, the will of the King urged with as great error as the former, and followed by them that would by it escape the payment and punishment of Parliament.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Ignorance and Clamor of the People.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The People that know not the law are accursed,</hi> Joh. 7.49. So said the Rulers of envy, and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> one of them held a better opinion of him whom the people magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:123763:2"/>to speake above all men. No law without hearing, and kowledge of the Fact, condemnes any man. The Rulers retort the Argument by reproach, and depart with disdaine every man to his owne house. Such is our sudden reproach not of the people for a good opinion of the Parliament, but of most Malignant parties that bid us search and see if any good come from such a Councell. <hi>Galilee</hi> was never a greater reproach to our Saviour, and <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> then this <hi>Parliament</hi> is to such as suffer for it, and we have a law to condemne it, for we have heard so much to be done by it, that all our knowne Lawes are against it.</p>
               <p>The fairest glosse <hi>Malignants</hi> have for their illegall actions, is to argue against the Parliament, and the Engine is, that their proceedings are against the knowne Laws, which so amuse the people in reading their pamphlets and Reasons that they resolve they better knew the Lawes then the Parliament it selfe, and such misery they suffer from it, that they must resume their owne power, and be their own Judges. When the King by ill Councell oppressed them, O then a <hi>Parliament</hi> to relieve them, and now they would be relieved against it by the known Laws. The truth is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lawes is removed from common capacities, and they are as principles of Arts and Sciences, of the which we say they are virtually contained in them, and deducible from them, <hi>nemo nascitur artifex,</hi> no man is borne an Artist to argue the truth from the first ground, and we say, <hi>t. ta scientia virtute continetur in principijs,</hi> that all knowledge is contained in the principles, and by great industry and study is fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out of them and certainly severall conclusions by discourse &amp; Argumentation is brought to light from them. If our Laws be so well known to the people, why do Lawyers take so great paines to inform them? Students we call them vainly, if their Clients be so learned, and the Lawyer takes money to advise for no advantage but his owne. What needs the Client to descend to Aguments, being armed sufficiently by his owne skill? How comes the case to fall out otherwise upon demurer or spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Verdict then he was informed? Judgment is reversed by a <hi>Writ of error,</hi> and from Court to Court, is brought at the last to the highest, and there setled for the soundest and surest resolution. They doe but disabuse the people that tell them of <hi>knowne Lawes</hi> against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and it is most abominable Hypocrisie to Angle their hearts to no other ends but to catch them in snares, to devoure them, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize over them, by blind obedience as the Pope does.</p>
               <p>For the second conveyance of the <hi>will of the King,</hi> the people tremble to thinke of it, and his personall commands come at the last to be their knowne Laws. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines doe but dally with Conscience, that we must obey the will of the King, which is condemned, <hi>Hos.</hi> 5.11. and no where commanded, and if we take obedience for subjection, it is not to the will, but the power of the Magistrate, and seeing all the care is taken for Kings, see what all the learned in the law say, <hi>potestas sua juris est non injuriae,</hi> the Kings power is justice, no injurie. <hi>Lex fraenum est potentiae,</hi> the Lawes are the bounds of the Kings power and command. <hi>Nihil potest, nisi id solum quod de jure potest,</hi> he can doe nothing but that onely which is just. <hi>Vicarius Dei dum facit justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, minister Diaboli dum declinet ad injuriam,</hi> he is Gods Vicar in doing of Iustice, and the Devils agent declining to injury. The <hi>King</hi> is invested with a judiciall power, not in his person but his Courts. His person is presumed by the Law to be ignorant of judicature, and the Acts of Ministery are below the Majestie of a <hi>King,</hi> and the Subject may suffer prejudice in many acts of justice, if such an <hi>Indecorum</hi> be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It's too meane for a Prince to be an <hi>Informer, Accuser, to arrest and compound them,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:123763:2"/>and such actions are judged void in law, and the Reason is evident, because the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, upon such actions, if unjust, can have no remedie against the Kings person, and so wrong shall be done, &amp; no law to right the oppressed, or punish the wrong doer. They wrong the people against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that by Prerogative above law call Conscience to obey, which is <hi>Scientia cum Deo,</hi> and not against him to please men.</p>
               <p>I have touched two sinnes in the People discontented by deceivers. First, <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> in judging of the Laws when they wring them. They are penny wise pound foolish, and follow a common opinion in compassion of themselves. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment exacts payments in forme of Law, and necessity compells them unto it, and Malignants say it is against law, as if they understood more then lawyers doe, which all of them pitch upon this Maxime, <hi>illud quod alias licitum non est, necessitas fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit licitum, et necessitas inducit privilegium, quod jure privatur.</hi> It's most certain the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in being judgeth of all accidents; and hath power to make lawfull that which without their judgement is unlawfull, and if necessity did not urge them, they would of it make no law, and the priviledge they have is warrantable upon the ground granted the King for the good of the Kingdome. Impositions and Ship money have been complained of as illegall, and by them that can condemne them, and therefore greater Judges then they that approved them, and yet their judgment had bin justifiable, if necessity had induced the priviledge, as now it does, and that in the judgement of them that cannot be contradicted, and yet does not every Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant manifest his malice to say there is no necessity because they cannot see it, and would have every man as blind as themselves. How irrationall is it that the King should declare the law against his great Counsell, when assuming it in his grants, Commissions, Proclamations under his great Seale, he is commonly judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all Courts to be abused, and the same made voyd, when the law is against them, and so judged to be by them that are sworne to doe Justice to such as suffer injurie by such unjust proceedings. His Majestie may easily protest what he will doe, and erre in the doing of it, by misinformation, and what credit can be given to any thing done or laid when the subjects are barbarously used for executing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly legall commands, and refusing illegall; by the <hi>Kings</hi> Army, his Counsellors and Abettors, and his supreme Counsell neglected and opposed, as able to doe nothing to save the people from desolation and destruction. If Subjects were not besotted with senceles men, they would suffer never themselves to be so circumvented by the will of the <hi>King,</hi> and known Laws against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as if the will of the King were above Law, or Law to be judged by it, and not by them that have alwaies to the King, and all sworne Judges declared laws. The will of the King may bee necessary to make a Law, it was never held so to declare it in any Court of Justice, and if Lawes may neither be, nor be expounded, but as the King pleaseth, we are in a miserable case in the proceedings of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and if that be true that is written and Printed in the conclusion of one Parliament, that it shall interpret the Lawes no otherwise, then the King and his sworne Judges will have it, Ship money and all Impositions shall stand good, that he and they judge to be law, and knowne laws shall be as the multitude murmure now for their money, and clamour out of the Parliament, shall they exact our estates against knowne Lawes, and the will of the King. When the King calls for it for his owne pleasure they cry our of oppression, and when the Parliament would have it for their owne good, they are still oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and would shift off all payments, caring for no common good, but that they may live at their owne ease without charges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:123763:3"/>
               <head>The Science and Conscience of Lawyers.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Woe unto you Lawyers, for you have taken away the Key of knowledge,</hi> Luk. 11.52. No marvell wee have so many Malignants of the multitude, when the Men of better parts misleade them, and keepe from them the key of knowledge. <hi>Ignoramus</hi> was once a pleasant comedy to play with the lawyers, but now Divines deserve the name, who ignorantly resolve Conscience without the Law. Dr. <hi>Ferne</hi> fell into his error by medling with a matter he understood not, for no Divine can rightly state the question between the King and <hi>Parliament, Parliament</hi> and People but he that knows the Lawes of the Land: and I wonder the Divine should deale with Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, not knowing where it is, for it is properly where all Causes may bee handled, and that is onely in Parliament, for it is not in the Kings power to handle any Causes out of the Courts of Justice, and of all Causes no one Court is capable, but the high Court of Parliament, and as the Person of the King is over all persons, so his power is onely in all Causes where their cognizance is, and if he will judge them out of Parliament, he passeth his limits, and the rule is, <hi>extra territorium jus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi, non paretur, impune,</hi> he that obeyes the command of any power, out of it's juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, shall be punished for it, and the Parliament must justly punish Delinquents that desert it, and seeke for safety and security in the shadow of their Soveraigne in his private capacity, for no law allowes him to protect offendors, kill and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, spoile and destroy his Subjects without processe of law (against <hi>Magna Charta c.</hi> 29.) whom he is bound by oath and Office to defend and preserve. It were well the Lawyers that pen the Kings papers would with their Science of the lawes use their Consciences to comfort and confirme the ignorant with more knowledge, then ignorantly the Divines have done; and seeing they speake so much of known lawes, they would know them better from those that the Kingdome hath alwayes made the best guides, and chiefe Judges, so much reproached for their care to curb the contentious, and cause the honest Subjects to bee supported against their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and wicked proceedings, in all their workes by open violation of laws.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Oath and Office of Iudges.</head>
               <p>Lawyers have liberty to plead their clyents causes according to their Science and Conscience, and they that are bad abuse both, and for their Fee feare not to say any thing: but Judges are sworne to doe right, and swerve as much as the other to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his humor, who hath given them their honour, and in hope of higher places hazzard heaven it selfe, and see no more then the blind, for bribes and brave places please them more then truth and; equity and when the King saies he and they shall interpret the lawes to the Parliament, and they shall passe no other judgement then warranted by them, we may be sure the wise men of our Kingdom shall be made fooles if they follow any such Verdict, as a Royall, but no righteous Edict to rule us all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Iury of <hi>12.</hi> men conclude every cause and Crime.</head>
               <p>Witnesses in the Word of God are counted most worthy of trust for the truth, and our Law with them proceeds further, to finde a <hi>Iury</hi> to heare the evidence, and the Judge to declare Law upon it, and then they passe the <hi>verdict,</hi> or finall fate of mens for unes, and what farre excells them, their very lives, when both now passe without Law against the Parliament, the supreme Judge of all causes kept from it
<pb facs="tcp:123763:3"/>by a Civill warre, the wickednesse whereof will presently appeare in adding the <hi>Divine</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> most coupled in this mystery, and without feare I will forme them both into such a composition as the world dreames not of; and the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>riest</hi> shall take no prejudice by mee, except the truth be prejudiciall to them to heare their errours, in the corruption of the purest calling. They are the two <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall pillars</hi> that beare up two bodies, that now lye dead in the street of the great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. <hi>Witnesses</hi> they are called, when they maintaine the truth, and <hi>Beasts</hi> when they oppose it; and they are two to two, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.11. <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> are the great mysteries in the matters that now maintaine the warres, and they rise up one against another, even in the same Kingdome, and the common ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity is come to our dores, and to open it will be evidence enough why <hi>Papists</hi> are become <hi>Protestants,</hi> in Divine <hi>Sermons, Service,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Our Sermons, they say, are morall perswasions, and our Religion without all <hi>formall heresie,</hi> or <hi>morall malignity:</hi> Our Service is a piece of their Masse-booke, and therefore so far good to heare it, and hope a part will bring in the wholes; and Masse, and Mattens, with all the marrow-bones, will be like <hi>Ezekiels boyling pot,</hi> where scumme and filth, with flesh, shall all boile together, and nothing be purged our of it, till all be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed in the fire, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.12.13. Fire and fury in our Nation is divine, and will not be done away, till all Romane mixtures be made to passe out of our land, and we left better then we have been. The Pot must be filled with the choice bones, and bones must burne under the pot. The scumme is in us, and woe be to us till it be out, and a thorough Reformation made, which God prosper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The two Witnesses, and the two Beasts.</head>
               <p>As the truth findes friends, so it hath enemies, <hi>Veritas odium parit,</hi> hatred is borne as a Monster against nature, which is regular, and if errour be, the birth is unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and so it happened in Paradise. <hi>God saw every thing he had made to be very good, Gen</hi> 1.31. The <hi>tree of good and evill, Gen.</hi> 2.17. was not so in being, but in use, and that was, to know mans maine temptation, though now the love of the creature tempt him more then the knowledge of the Creatour. The monster appeares in mans apparell, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 7. and the leaves cover them, whose fruit made them naked; and ever since the shels of truth have been the shadowes to hide errours, which makes the Apostle call this <hi>last Aposlasie,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1. <hi>hypocrisie,</hi> vers. 2. and it is of such lyers as live nearest Christians, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. as the Court of the Temple is so neare it, that it containes it, and corrupts it, and nothing but the first measure can make good truth against it, from the which we have declined ever since the end of the <hi>fourth Century,</hi> which followes the <hi>Red Dragon, Rev.</hi> 12.8. and appeares in <hi>two Beasts,</hi> wherof the one bears his <hi>Crownes, Rev.</hi> 13.1. and the other his <hi>Priesthood, Rev.</hi> 13.11. The first is an Army of Seculars that fight with the Lamb with ten horns, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17 14. and the other of sacred persons, that set upon him with his owne Hornes which are two, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13 11. the secular Hornes are seduced, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.13. or subdued, <hi>Dan</hi> 7.8.24.25. The secular Hornes held the sacred Hornes under till they were expulsed quite out of Rome, and the servile province thereof to Emperours and Kings, became the Soveraign Lordship of the Pope and for whom <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> seduced or subdued have made all the stirre and they that will not stand for him are withstood with all the subtilty and cruelty that wit or wickednesse can worke by warre, or secret contrivances. No marvell our King protests our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection without the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nay against it, for so are both the Monsters of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish
<pb facs="tcp:123763:4"/>braines, which they beleeve not when they have hatched them in hatred of us and our King. The <hi>Councell of Basil</hi> decreed a generall <hi>Synod</hi> to be above the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the reason is from a <hi>Senate</hi> above the King, and the Reason thus, all States have remedies to right themselves against ruine by a selfe preservation against one man. That all by one should perish is unreasonable, and therefore in kingdomes the highest Courts command all, and take care for common safety. These miscreants of mischiefe have since the <hi>Councell of Basil</hi> made one Bishop above all Synods and Senates, and because the great Senate of <hi>England</hi> is not under their errour, they cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate one against both Pope and Councell, and say, certainly the King is supreme, not over all persons, but the very <hi>Parliament.</hi> A doctrine they never taught before this day; for all <hi>Popish Bishops</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> ever held the King to be under them in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and God forbid the <hi>Bishops</hi> removed, the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> should doe as they have done, remove the King. But marke these men that are for the King, and what they say in both <hi>oaths of Allegeance and Supremacy.</hi> They say the oath of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy was unlawfull in the dayes of <hi>Henry the eighth,</hi> the first that found it out, and <hi>Bishop Fisher</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> dyed Martyrs, because he was of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to sweare any man but the <hi>Pope</hi> head of the Catholike Church, is an horrible sinne: but his sonne <hi>King Edward</hi> was head of another Church of his own making, and to be head of that all good Catholikes may sweare it; but that the King is their head is most hatefull in their Religion. We say the Catholike Church hath no head but Jesus Christ, and that Kings are no heads of it, but of all such persons as professe it in their Dominions, which <hi>Papists</hi> will not professe, for as Catholikes they have no head but the <hi>Pope,</hi> and to him they are sworne to defend his Catholike Church against Protestants, and to die as <hi>Fisher</hi> and <hi>Moore</hi> died Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, that is, Rebells, for they dyed not for Religion, <hi>King Hemy</hi> still professing their Catholike Faith, but not the Popes supremacy in his kingdome. But now these wise men, like <hi>weather-cockes,</hi> turning with the times, and seeing the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against them, set the King against it, and above it, that he may do for them, to undoe himself and whole Kingdom. And now see the <hi>two</hi> and <hi>ten hornes</hi> set against <hi>Christ,</hi> &amp; meditate seriously on the mystery. The most of the <hi>Ministers</hi> are malignants; for what makes them with the Papists to put the king above his Parliament, and plead conscience to the people, but that they may obey the King against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> because the king must do all things, and without him nothing can be done, and yet all he can doe is to <hi>Bills of new Laws,</hi> which is only this, if he grant them <hi>le Roy voet,</hi> if he wil advise before he grant them he saies, <hi>le roy ad visera,</hi> &amp; good reason the <hi>king</hi> should be ruled by his own <hi>judgment,</hi> the judgment of his sworn judges, his Counsellers, both privie and publique, and til he find just cause to grant to suspend his voie, but not by violence compell his <hi>counsell</hi> to do nothing, because he cannot or will not do this: the parliament is bound by the great trust of the kingdom to do all things to preserve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Conclusion to all Benevolent and Malevolent English men.</head>
               <p>Country-men, what is your contention ene with another? can you tell the cause of your combate? call to mind your mustered mistaken truths. First, you speak of known laws, have you any <hi>against, above, beside,</hi> or <hi>without</hi> the <hi>Parliament?</hi> If you have, who told you so? Malignants without doubt, and never deny your selves to be such, if you hold such an opinion against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for never durst any person declare what was law without the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and now every man will be a judge, and resume his power to passe sentence upon them he hath elected to be the mouth
<pb facs="tcp:123763:4"/>to declare without contradiction the mind and meaning of all just and legall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. Secondly, you make much of the will of the King, and his personall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and hold them good against both Houses, and that you are bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science rather to obey such Edicts of injustice, then the verdicts of Judges above all Juries, and processes whatsoever. An infallible evidence of error to argue obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the will of one man, when many are to be obeyed in the same power. It is not the will of the king that makes any law, and if law be the rule of our wills, the sole will of the king cannot warrant what we doe. The judgement of any Court is more to be obeyed then the pleasure of the king, <hi>Quod principi placet, legis non habet vigorem,</hi> and the position is true, that <hi>Kings sedneed, may injure the Common-wealth, but the Parliament cannot,</hi> because they are most proper Judges of the Kingdome, and the imminent dangers therof. Thirdly, the right of the Subject as it is in himselfe by inherence or inheritance is not known or held against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> His person is free, fortunes firme, and what he hath he may hold, but not by his own will, the trust is out of his own hands, and for common good nothing may be kept to our owne use, required from us by them we have trusted. The king and kingdome hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all to the two Houses, and if they were not worthy, we should never have bin so rash as to have left such a power in them by whom we may perish. We may perish by the King but the people never perished by the <hi>Parliament</hi> Many are trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported against both Houses to hate their proceedings, that so great trust by the Act of Continuance is committed unto them and such confidence reposed in them, that the King hath lest his Royall prerogative in their hands, not to dissolve the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> till they please, and make his grant so great ingratitude in them, that they would have all men grieve with the King that he hath lost his wonted power to dissolve at pleasure that body he hath convented to correct the whole Kingdome, such are the words of Malignants to make them odious, as if they had circumvented the King, and drawne him into a snare, <hi>promising to make him great, rich and honourable,</hi> and doing the contrary. The scandalls cast upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> are such slanders as may be wiped off from them with ease, if men were as earnest to understand as they are to argue. His Majestie had reason to call and continue his <hi>Parliament</hi> to pacifie his people in <hi>Scotland,</hi> pay them for their wrongs, and support such-publique charges both by Sea and Land, and that in all his Kingdomes as is almost incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible. The causes may be knowne by all. <hi>Scotland</hi> was provoked by our Bishops to receive their Discipline by compulsion. <hi>Ireland</hi> is in Rebellion to raise up Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery with the perdition of all the people that are Protestants. A Popish Army is raised in <hi>England;</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> deserted, Delinquents protected, the People de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, Malignants suffered to muster forces to fall upon the quiet People, drive them from their possessions, purloine as they have, wast their habitations, and cause the two Houses to be loaden with all the cares of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and yet these cry out, <hi>how much have they promised his Majestie, and how little doe they performe. They tell the King they can doe him no wrong, because he is not capable to doe it or receive it. That they take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from him, because he had never any thing of his owne,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It were end lesse to heare the hatred of these horrible Malignants, that are sorry the King hath so little to give them, and therefore they say all is his, and make his authority sufficient to take away every mans estate, which to sue out of their hands, the two Houses can handle nothing of any other concernment, then to prevent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent dangers, as fast as their enemies create them, and if the safety of the People
<pb facs="tcp:123763:5"/>be the safety of the Prince, and their riches and plenty the way to make him great, rich, and honourable, they can effect nothing for him before their good and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity bee procured. His Majestie makes the interpretation of the Statute of the 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. to provide for the meanest Subject in the Kingdome above the King, and why? Because they are for Treason that destroyes the Kingdome, and say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the King. I hope the King is safe in that Subject, and am sure out of it he hath no safety, and as the case now stands, the Kingdome is in danger by an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my with him, which to preserve the Kingdome no man can see it, and truely how it should preserve the King in a riddle too, whom they have exposed to ruine with themselves, not by the Kingdome, but the preservation of it out of their hands, which if they prevaile, they may promise the person security, but the King can have none, if his Kingdomes perish. Take all, and wonder at the Wisdome of them that seeke to make us all Fooles.</p>
               <p>First knowne Lawes against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Secondly, the will of the King against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Thirdly, the Liberty of the Subjects against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their property in their goods against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Fiftly, their power against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Sixtly, their Commission of <hi>Array</hi> against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Seventhly, their Army against the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Eightly, the exaction of the Peoples goods against the Parliament. Ninthly, the arming of Papists against the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> Tenthly, the personall Commands of the King against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all because the King will not joyne with them from whom he cannot bee dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, or doe any thing without them, and if they aske whether they can doe any thing without him? I answer all things but the making of new Lawes. They may declare Lawes without him, as a Court having his Authority, and the Authority of the whole Kingdome. <hi>Le Roy voet,</hi> and <hi>le Roy ad visera</hi> are onely personally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in new grants, but what is granted they may execute, as to declare doubis of Lawes, redresse injuries, punish offenders, cancell the Kings grants; provide for imminent dangers, and by Ordinances command such obedience as may secure the Kingdome, and the fallacy the <hi>Parliament</hi> can make no new Lawes without the King, therefore they can doe nothing, is from one particular to conclude a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, not this therefore nothing, as if this were all, when many things may be done that require neither <hi>Le Roy voet,</hi> or <hi>Le Roy ad visera,</hi> for if the King may grant or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and so to deale, determine all, he may dally and delay judgement, as he pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which God forbid.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>